<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonition to all such as shall intend hereafter to enter the state of matrimony godlily and aggreeably to lawes. ... Set forth by the most reuerend father in God, Mathew Archbishop of Canterbury, Primate of England, and Metropolitane.</title>
            <title>Admonition--for the necessitie of the presente tyme tyll a furder consultation--to all suche as shall intende hereafter to enter the state of matrimonye godly and agreablye to lawes</title>
            <author>Parker, Matthew, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19289.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845891</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845891</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10822</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08995)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10822)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1667:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonition to all such as shall intend hereafter to enter the state of matrimony godlily and aggreeably to lawes. ... Set forth by the most reuerend father in God, Mathew Archbishop of Canterbury, Primate of England, and Metropolitane.</title>
                  <title>Admonition--for the necessitie of the presente tyme tyll a furder consultation--to all suche as shall intende hereafter to enter the state of matrimonye godly and agreablye to lawes</title>
                  <author>Parker, Matthew, 1504-1575.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Turner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1630]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Text in English; catalogue has Latin and English in parallel columns.</note>
                  <note>Heading line 2 ends: "of ma-"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19291.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consanguinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="laws_of_matrimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:10822:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ADMONITION TO ALL SUCH AS SHALL
INTEND HERE AFTER TO ENTER THE STATE OF MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRIMONY,
GODLILY AND AGREEABLY TO LAWES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, that they contract not with ſuch perſons as be hereafter expreſſed, nor with any of like degree, againſt the law of God, &amp; the laws of the
Realm.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that they make no ſecret contracts, without conſent and counſell of their Parents or Elders, under whoſe authority they be:
contrary to Gods lawes and mans ordinances.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they contract not anew with any other upon divorce and ſeperation made by the Iudge for a time, the lawes yet ſtanding
to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Arriage is honourable among all men, and the bed undefiled. But whoremongers and adulterers God will judg, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>To avoid fornication, let every man have his wife, and let every woman have her husband. He that cannot containe, let him marry: For better
it is to marry, then to burn. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Vnto the married I commaund, not I, but the Lord: Let not the Wife depart from her Husband. But if ſhe depart let them remaine unmarried, or be
reconciled unto her husband. And let not the Husband put away his Wife.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chart_of_matrimonial_laws">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LEVITICUS. XVIII. &amp; XX.</bibl>
None ſhall come neer to any of the kinred of his fleſh to uncover her ſhame: I am the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>¶A man may not marry his</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Secundus gradus in linea recta aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Avia</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Grandmother</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Avi relicta</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Grandfathers wife</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af</cell>
                        <cell>Proſocrus, vel ſocrus magna.</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>Wives Grandmother.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Secundus grad: in aequalis, in linea tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa
aſcendente.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Amita</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>Fathers ſiſter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Matertera</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>Mothers ſiſter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Patrui relicta</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>Fathers brothers wife</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Avunculi relicta</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>Mothers brothers wife</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Amita uxoris</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>Wives fathers ſiſter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Matertera uxoris.</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>Wives mothers ſiſter.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Primus gradus in linea recta aſcendente.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Mater</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>Mother</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Noverca</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>Stepmother</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Socrus</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>Wives mother.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Primus gradus in linea recta deſcendente.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Filia</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>Daughter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Privigna</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>Wives daughter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Nurus</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>Sonnes wife.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Primus gradus aequalis in linea tranſver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſali.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Soror.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>Siſter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Soror uxoris</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>Wives ſiſter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Fratris relicta</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>Brothers wife.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Secundus gradus in linea recta deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Neptis ex filio</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>Sonnes daughter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Neptis ex filia</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>Daughters daughter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Pronurus. i. relicta nepotis ex filio</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>Sonnes ſonnes wife</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Pronurus. i. relicta nepotis ex filia</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>Daughters ſonnes wife</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Privigni filia</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>Wives ſonnes daughter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Privignae filia</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>Wives daughters daughter.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Secundus gradus inaequalis, in linea tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali
deſcendente.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Neptis ex fratre</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>Brothers daughter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Nepis ex ſorore</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>Siſters daughter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Nepotis ex fratre relicta</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>Brothers ſonnes wife</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Nepotis ex ſorore relicta</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>Siſters ſonnes wife</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Neptis uxoris ex fratre</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>Wives brothers daughter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Neptis uxoris ex ſorore.</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>Wives ſiſters daughter.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A woman may not marry with her</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Secundus gradus in recta linea aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>Grandfather</cell>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Avus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Grandmothers husband</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Aviae relictus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>Husbands grandfather.</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Proſocer, vel ſocer magnus.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Secundus gradus inaequalis in linea
tranſverſali aſcendente.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>Fathers brother.</cell>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Patruus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>Mothers brother</cell>
                        <cell>Con</cell>
                        <cell>Avunculus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>Fathers ſiſters huſband</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Amitae relictus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>Mothers ſiſters huſband</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Materterae relictus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands fathers brother</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Patruus mariti</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands mothers brother.</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Avunculus mariti.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Primus gradus in linea recta deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>Father</cell>
                        <cell>Con</cell>
                        <cell>Pater</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>Stepfather</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Vitricus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands father.</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Socer</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Primus gradus in linea recta deſcendente.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>Sonne</cell>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Filius</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands ſonne</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Privignus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>Daughters huſband.</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Gener.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Primus gradus aequalis in linea tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>Brother</cell>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Frater</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands brother</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Levir</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>Siſters huſband.</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Sororis relictus.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Secundus gradus in linea recta deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>Sonnes ſonne</cell>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Nepos ex filio</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>Daughters ſonne.</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Nepos ex filia</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>Sonnes daughters huſband</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Progener. i. relictus neptis ex filio.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>Daughters daughters huſband</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Progener. i. relictus neptis ex filia.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands ſonnes ſonne</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Privigni filius.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands daughters ſonne.</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Privignae filius.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Secund. gradus inaequalis, in linea tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali
deſcendente</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>Brothers ſonne</cell>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Nepos ex fratre</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>Siſters ſonne</cell>
                        <cell>Con.</cell>
                        <cell>Nepos ex ſorore</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>Brothers daughters huſband</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Neptis ex fratre relictus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>Siſters daughters huſband</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Neptis ex ſorore relictus</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands brothers ſonne</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Leviris filius. i. nepos mariti ex fratre</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>Huſbands ſiſters ſonne.</cell>
                        <cell>af.</cell>
                        <cell>Gloris filius. i. nepos mariti ex ſorore</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <p>1 <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is to be noted, that thoſe perſons which be in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
line, aſcendent &amp; deſcendent, cannot marry toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
although they be never ſo far aſunder in degree.</p>
            <p>2 It is alſo to be noted, that conſanguinity &amp; affinity
(letting and diſſolving Matrimony) is contracted as
well in them &amp; by them, which is of kinred by the one
ſide, as in &amp; by them, which be of kinred by both ſides.</p>
            <p>3 Item, that by the Laws, conſanguinity and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity
(letting and diſſolving Matrimony) is contracted as well by unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
company of man and woman as by unlawful marriage.</p>
            <p>4 Item, in contracting betwixt perſons doubtfull, which be not expreſſed
in this Table, it is moſt ſure, firſt to conſult with men learned in the lawes,
to underſtand what is lawfull, what is honeſt and expedient, before the fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing
of their contracts.</p>
            <p>5 Item, that no Parſon, Vicar or Curate, ſhall ſolemnize Matrimony out
of his or their Cure or pariſh Church or Chappel, and ſhall not ſolemnize
the ſame in private houſes, nor lawleſſe or exempt Churches, under the pains
of the law, forbidding the ſame. And that the Curate have the Certificates,
when the parties dwell in divers places.</p>
            <p>6 Item, the bands of matrimony ought to be openly denounced in the
Church by the Miniſter, three ſeverall Sundaies or Feſtivall daies, to the
end that who will and can alledge any impediment, may be heard, and that
ſtay may be made till further triall, if any exception be made there againſt
it upon ſufficient caution.</p>
            <p>7 Item, who ſhall maliciouſly object a frivolous impediment againſt a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
matrimony, to diſturb the ſame, is ſubject to the paines of the Law.</p>
            <p>8 Item, who ſhall preſume to contract in the degrees prohibited (though
he do it ignorantly) beſides that the fruit of ſuch copulation may be judged
unlawfull, is alſo puniſhable at the ordinaries diſcretion.</p>
            <p>9 Item, if any miniſter ſhall conjoyne any ſuch, or ſhall be preſent at
ſuch contracts making, he ought to be ſuſpended from his miniſterie for
three years: and otherwiſe to be puniſhed according to lawes.</p>
            <p>10 Item, it is further ordained, that noe Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, do
Preach, treat, or expound of his own voluntary invention, any matter of
controverſie in the Scriptures, if he be under the degree of maſter of Art,
except he be licenſed by his Ordinary thereunto, but onely for the inſtruction
of the people: read the Homilies, allready ſet forth, and ſuch other form of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
as ſhall be hereafter by authority publiſhed: and ſhall not innovate, or
alter any thing in the Church, or uſe any old Rite, or Cerimony, which be
not ſet forth by publick authority.</p>
            <byline>Set forth by the moſt Reverend Father in God, <hi>Mathew</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Primate of <hi>England,</hi> and Metropolitane.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
